Lurie, Andrea; Papers apap051
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Andrea Lurie Papers
1913-1986
1967-1982
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
apap051
2.24 cubic ft.
This collection contains materials related to the women's movement and lesbian rights in New York State, especially the Capital Region in the 1970s, as well as materials related to Lurie's professional efforts as an archeologist.
Biographical History
Andrea Lurie was an active member of the womens movement in the New York Capital Region during the 1960s, 1970s, and 1980s. This included founding and working with such organizations as Capital District Women (CDW), Women's Counseling Collective, and Tri-City Women's Center. She was involved in the planning of the Womens "Revolution", a utopian society that would promote equality, same-sex relationships, and polyamory while discouraging traditional family dynamics. Lurie was also responsible for executing the Women's Day March in Albany, N.Y.
Professionally, Andrea Lurie was an archeologist. She used her education to promote feminism and better understand the social dynamics responsible for misogyny. A majority of the published materials within the collection relate to her research.
Scope and Contents
The collection includes materials related to the women's movement and lesbian rights with an emphasis on the Capital Region of New York. Andrea Lurie collected photographs from Women's Day in Albany, posters, material related to projects in Albany, correspondence, drafts of manuscripts, and Lurie's own speeches. Records of particular interest are those of the group Capital District Women and the Women's Counseling Collective. Also included are pamphlets, newsletters, journals, and periodicals.
Having worked as an archeologist in her professional career, there are also materials related to archeology including academic journals, conference materials, and archeological societies. Though many of the materials only tangentially relate to the feminist movement, they help to show the extent of Lurie's personal and professional endeavors.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection has no series and is arranged alphabetically.
Separated Materials
The archivist transferred six volumes of "Signs: Journal of Women in Culture and Society" to the book division of the Special Collections, including: Volume 1 Nos. 1, 2, 3 (parts 1 and 2), 4; Volume 2 Nos. 1, 2, 3; Volume 3 Nos. 1, 2, 3, 4; Volume 4 Nos. 1, 2, 3, 4; Volume 5 Nos. 1, 2, 3; and Volume 6 Nos. 1 and 2. They will be catalogued and included in the University Library Catalog.
Acquisition Information
All items in this manuscript group were donated to the University Libraries, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives by Andrea Lurie in 1994 June.
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Lurie, Andrea; Women; Human Sexuality and Gender Identity; Albany, New York; Women's rights -- New York (State); Homosexuality -- Law and legislation -- New York (State); Posters; Minutes; Speeches; Archeology; Journal
- 1st New York State Women's Meeting, Meeting Materials, 1977 July 8; 1977 July 10 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- American Journal of Sociology, Vol. 78 No. 4, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- "An Army of Lovers Shall Not Fail", Undated (Flat-file 1)
- Archaeological Conferences, 1970; 1974 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Archaeology of Eastern North America Journal Vol. 1-3, 1973-1975 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- "Are Men Really the Enemy" An Examination, Undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Aurora Magazine, Feminist Alternatives Issue, No. 4, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Bulletin of The Archaeological Society of New Jersey, No. 31 Fall/Winter, Spring/Summer, No. 32 Spring/Summer,No.33, 1974-1976 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Capital District Women, Organizational Records, ca. 1972-1975 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Capital District Women Planning Meeting Minutes, 1972-1974 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Capital District Women: Revolution, Journal of Meeting Minutes, 1973 June-1973 December (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Civil Rights Digest Magazine "Sexism and Racism: Feminist Perspective" Issue, Spring 1974 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Collage, Production "Because I Said So," Interart Theatre, Women's Interart Center, New York City, Playwright Myrna Lamb, Photographer Jill Lynne, Undated (Flat-file 1)
- Country Women Journal, Vol. 1 No. 7-8, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- "Cowrie Lesbian/feminist" Magazine, Vol. 1, No. 5, 1974 February (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Eastern States Archeological Federation Bulletins, No. 26-29, 1967 June; 1969 July; 1970 July (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Eastern States Archeological Federation Proceedings of the Annual Meeting, 1974 October 18-1974 October 20 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- "Everywoman" Newspaper, 1971 January 1; 1971 January 22; 1971 February 5 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Expensive People, a Screenplay by Eleanor Perry, Undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
- "Female Studies" Journal 6 & 7 by The Feminist Press, 1972-1973 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- "Female Studies" Journal 9 & 10 by The Feminist Press, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- "Indian Record" Magazine, Special Issue: Indian Women, 1969 February (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Life Magazine "Remarkable American Women 1776-1976" Special Report (Oversized 1, Folder 1)
- "Majority Report" Newspaper Vol. 2, No. 12; Vol. 4, Nos. 21, 25; Vol. 5, No. 14, 1973; 1975 (Oversized 1, Folder 2)
- "Make History - with Your Vote! Judge Nanette Dembitz for Court of Appeals, Elect the First Woman to New York's Highest Court", ca. 1972 (Flat-file 1)
- "Me and Them Sirens Running All Night Long" by Susan Cavin, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- ""Mother Emancipator:" The Meaning of Jane Addams' Sickness and Cure" by G.J Barker- Benfield, Winter 1979 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- "Ms." Magazine 10th Anniversary Edition, 1982 August (Box 1, Folder 23)
- "Ms." Magazine Preview Issue, Spring 1972 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- New York Introduces "Ms." Magazine, Special Year-End Double Issue, 1971 December 20 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- "No More Fun and Games" A Journal of Female Liberation, Issues 2-5, 1969-1971 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- "Norman Mailer: The Prisoner of Sex" Harper's Magazine, 1971 March (Box 1, Folder 27)
- "Off Our Backs: a Women's News Journal" Vol. 2 No. 4; Vol. 3 No. 5; Vol. 4 No. 6, 11-12; Vol. 5 No. 8-11; Vol. 6 No. 2-5; Vol. 7 No. 1-2, 1971; 1973-1977 (Oversized 1, Folder 3)
- "Our Bodies Our Selves: A Course By and For Women" First Edition, Second Printing, 1971 April (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Program for Symposium on the Religions of the Eastern Woodlands Indians, 1968 April 6 (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Research Materials, ca. 1967-1974 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- "Sisterhood: Make It Real, Woman's Studio Collective, New Paltz", Undated (Flat-file 1)
- "Speak Out: a Feminist Journal," Susan B. Anthony Cover Art, Poster, 1973 (Flat-file 1)
- Speak Out Newsletter, 1973 December (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Speeches, Andrea Lurie, 1971-1973; Undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
- "Studies in the Anthropology of Visual Communication" Vol. 2 No. 2, Fall 1975 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Susan Saxe and Assata Shakur Benefit, Sponsored by the Women's Defense Committee, March 20, Undated (Flat-file 1)
- Talking Leaf, Publication of the Los Angeles Indian Center, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- "The Archeological Society of New Jersey" Newsletter, No. 84-89, 99 and President's Report, 1970-1973; 1976; Undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
- "The Archeological Society of New Jersey" Organization Materials, 1972; 1974 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- "The Chesopiean" A Journal of North American Archaeology, Vol. 13, Nos. 1-2, 1975 February-1975 April (Box 2, Folder 8)
- "The Female Experience Magazine", from the Editors of Psychology Today, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- "The New York State Wampum Collection: The Case for the Integrity of Cultural Treasures" by William N. Fenton, 1971 December (Box 2, Folder 10)
- "The Passover Haggadah" rendered by Abraham Regelson, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- "The Review of Radical Political Economics: The Political Economy of Women", 1972 July (Box 2, Folder 12)
- "The Second Wave: A Magazine of New Feminism", Vol. 1, Nos. 1-4, 1972-1973 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- "The Second Wave: A Magazine of New Feminism", Vol. 3 Nos. 1-4; Vol. 4 Nos. 1-2, 1973-1975 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- The Spokeswoman Newsletter, Vol. 1, Nos. 1, 5-12, 14, 1970-1971 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- "The Suffragette" Newspaper, No. 35, Vol. 1, 1913 June 13 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- The Womens Counselling Collective- Statement of Purpose, 1976 April (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Time Magazine Special Issue "The American Woman", 1972 March 20 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- "Trans action" Social Science and Modern Society, Special Combined Issue, Vol. 1, No. 1/2, 1970 November-1970 December (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Tri-City Women's Center Newsletter, Vol. 7, No.9, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- "Women: A Bibliography" by Lucinda Cisler, 1970 July-1970 October (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Women: A Journal of Liberation Magazine, Spring and Summer, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Women: A Journal of Liberation Magazine, Vol. 3 No. 2-3; Vol. 4 No. 1, 3; Vol. 5 No. 2, 1972; 1975-1977 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- "Women In Cross-Cultural Perspective: A Preliminary Sourcebook", 1971 November (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Women's Day, Albany, Photographs, Undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Women's Day, Washington Park, Albany, August 26, Undated (Flat-file 1)
- "Women's Liberation: Major Writings of the Radical Feminists" Magazine, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Women's Organizations Membership Lists, 1972-1974 (Box 4, Folder 3)